

# Todd M. Ellis

#### ATA ANALYST & STATISTICAL PROGRAMMER

Hobart, Tasmania, Australia

□ +61 466 683 552 | ► toddellis.wa@gmail.com | □ 0000-0002-4410-8676 | □ Todd-Ellis-4 | □ toddellis | □ tmichaelellis | ► tootstorm

## PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY.

I'm a data analyst and scientist with a background in forest ecology, physical geography, and higher education. I've worked as an analyst in a wide variety of laboratory, field, and office settings across the United States and Australia. Over the course of my career, I've developed novel mathematical tools and statistical models; maintained relational databases and statistical packages used for conducting data analysis and producing standardized reports; trained countless staff, students, and volunteers; and managed complex and critical projects. My research has been published in high-impact, peer-reviewed journals, and I'm also skilled at conveying complex data and information to both casual and experienced stakeholders.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **Doctor of Philosophy, Biological Sciences**

University of Tasmania 2019 - present

- · Dissertation: Dynamic mapping and analysis of New South Wales fire regimes: Past, present, and future
- Supervisors: Drs. Grant J. Williamson and David M.J.S. Bowman

#### **Master of Science, Geography**

WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Bellingham, WA, USA

Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

2013 - 2016

- Thesis: Climatic drivers of western spruce budworm outbreaks in the Okanogan Highlands
- · Supervisor: Dr. Aquila Flower

#### Bachelor of Science, Physical Geography / Geology

TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY

San Marcos, TX, USA

2007 - 2012

### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

Data Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (part-time / full-time)

2021-02 - present

- Developing statistical models and tools for meeting target university milestones
- Managing design and implementation of broad-scale university ML models for directing future university marketing, funding, and course creation
- · Designing and implementing programming and data analytics training seminars for institution staff
- · Overseeing development of internal reporting and statistical packages

Adjunct Researcher Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: College of Sciences and Engineering (full-time)

2019-09 - present

- · Developing complex data-processing and analysis pipelines using high-performance computing and big data
- Overseeing multi-year projet design and implementation addressing wildfire and global climate change challenges
- · Managing custom platform for interactive web-mapping, on-the-fly statistical analyses, and novel data visualisation
- Collaborating with national and international research teams tackling climate change risk and mitigation

Sustainability Analyst Sandy Bay, TAS, Australia

University of Tasmania: Division of Future Students (casual)

2019-10 - 2021-02

2018-12 - 2019-05

• Processed, analysed, and reported data to promote and review institution programmes

- Developed pipelines for automating data cleaning and collation
- Prepared data and briefings for global institution rankings

APEX SYSTEMS: APPLE, INC. (CONTRACT)

Promoted nation-wide sustainability targets using data dashboards and reports

Data & GIS Analyst Austin, TX, USA

• Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets

- Developed and standardised data-processing methods for vector and multispectral raster datasets
- · Managed and processed corporate GIS databases using data-driven software and programming languages
- Prepared statistical summaries, models, and analytical reports
- · Led research and development projects to define novel methodologies for geospatial data

#### **Faculty Research Assistant**

OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY: USDA FOREST SERVICE FORESTRY SCIENCES LABORATORY (CONTRACT)

2017-11 - 2018-06

Wenatchee, WA, USA

- Converted complex data and findings into academic and government reports
- Developed explanatory models for sustainable forest management under climate change
- Created and maintained relational databases for government research
- Gathered and analysed ecological data using statistical software

#### **Biological Science Technician II**

Ridgefield, WA, USA

2017-08 - 2017-11

2017-01 - 2017-11

WASHINGTON DEPARTMENT OF FISH AND WILDLIFE: REGION 5 (CONTRACT)

- Applied QA/QC to develop electronic biological data collection system and relational database
- Analysed biological fisheries data for state government research reporting
- · Collected and recorded biological data for government research and both commercial and tribal fisheries
- Designed, built, and maintained department, fisheries, and commercial research equipment

#### CONSULTING \_\_\_\_\_

2020-08	Predicting fire behaviour using historical satellite imagery	AUD\$1,000
	Frontier Development Lab	AUD\$1,000
2019-06	Post-fire logging effects on reburn severity	USD\$2.500
	USDA Forest Service	03032,300
2018-08	Restoration treatment effects on ponderosa pine growth sensitivity to climate	USD\$2,500
	USDA Forest Service	

BEACON HILL ELEMENTARY SCHOOL

HONC	DURS	
2022-11	Future Students Staff Excellence 2022 Sustainability Award	
	University of Tasmania	
2021-10	NSW Environment, Energy and Science (DPIE) Eureka Prize for Applied Environmental Research	AUD\$10,000
	Australian Museum	
2021-09	Future Students Staff Excellence 2021 Sustainability Award	
	University of Tasmania	
2021-08	Certifi-Cat of Appreciation	
	Ten Lives Cat Centre	
2019-09	Tasmania Graduate Research Scholarship (3.5x)	AUD\$28,000 p.a.
	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	
2019-09	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub Top-Up (3.5x)	AUD\$5,000 p.a.
	NSW Bushfire Risk Management Research Hub	
2018-06	Best Fish and Wildlife Science	
	Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife	
2017-10	Conservation Award	
	Weekington Department of Fish and Wildlife	

washington bepartment or rish and whathe	
2017-10 Conservation Award	
Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife	
VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE	
Foster Parent	Hobart, TAS, Australia
Ten Lives Cat Centre	2020-05 - present
Animal Handler	New Braunfels, TX, USA
Humane Society of the New Braunfels Area	2018-08 - 2019-01
Animal Handler	Wenatchee, WA, USA
Wenatchee Valley Humane Society	2018-03 - 2018-08
Technology Tutor	Wenatchee, WA, USA
North Central Regional Library	2018-01 - 2018-08
Geographic Information Systems Technician	Portland, OR, USA
PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY	2017-01 - 2017-11
Assistant Librarian	Kelso, WA, USA